"The Benefits of Fenugreek for
Preventing and Treating Diabetes"
The spice fenugreek is
considered to be one of
humanity’s oldest medicinal plants.
What can it do?
In my last video on fenugreek,
I explored the evidence showing
it can improve sexual
function in both men and women,
decrease menstrual pain,
and boost milk production
in lactating mothers.
And what are the side effects?
Fifteen randomized controlled
trials show, on average,
a significant improvement
in cholesterol levels.
And a dozen other studies show
significant improvements
in both long- and short-term blood
sugar control in diabetics
and prediabetics using an average of
about a half teaspoon a day
over a period of an
average of two months.
Results clearly indicate that
fenugreek is an inexpensive,
low-risk dietary supplement
that has potential
to improve blood sugar
control in diabetes.
What exactly is the mechanism by
which it lowers blood sugars?
There’s a peculiar amino
acid in fenugreek
that increases insulin
release from the pancreas.
The peculiar 4-hydroxyisoleucine
has been described as
an efﬁcient compound in the
regulation of insulin secretion.
Due to the fact that it
acts as a secretagogue
in the presence of elevated
blood glucose concentrations,
it has been proposed for
the potential treatment
of insulin resistance,
diabetes, and obesity.
There’s a class of diabetes drugs
that does the same thing:
sulfonylureas, sold as like Glucotrol,
glyburide, Micronase, glipizide.
The problem is that they
increase insulin secretion
whether you need it or not,
and so there’s a risk
of severe hypoglycemia,
driving your blood sugars too low.
The funky fenugreek amino
acid, on the other hand,
only boosts it when you need it.
When your blood sugars are
normal, it has no effect.
It only seems to stimulate
extra insulin release
when you need it most, when
your blood sugars are high.
What these researchers did,
was after consent was obtained
from family members,
pancreases were obtained
from brain-dead organ donors.
Put the insulin-secreting
cells in a petri dish
at a low blood sugar concentration,
and they release a little insulin,
and at high blood sugar levels
they release more insulin.
That makes sense.
That’s what they’re supposed to do,
since insulin is the
hormone your body releases
when trying to bring
down your blood sugars.
Add in some of that
fenugreek amino acid, though,
and you can boost insulin
production. Great!
But if that happened even at the
low blood sugar concentration too,
it would be like the drugs
and you could dip too low,
but no, when you don’t need extra
insulin, no fenugreek effect.
What about the role of fenugreek
in the prevention of type 2 diabetes?
A 3-year randomized controlled
study of the efficacy
of fenugreek on men and women
diagnosed with prediabetes.
Those randomized to fenugreek
were told to take about
one and a third teaspoons of
fenugreek powder twice a day
before meals, and both the fenugreek
and the control groups that
didn’t get any fenugreek
were both given identical
diet and lifestyle advice.
And, by the end of the study,
the cumulative incidence rate
of diabetes was reduced significantly
in the fenugreek group.
Check it out. Those who didn’t
get the fenugreek
had a four times higher
chance of developing diabetes,
and you could already see
the groups starting to diverge
within six months, and all
from just a few cents worth
of a spice, every day.
If you yourself want to
intimately support this kind of
amazing research in the future,
be sure to register at organdonor.gov.